[
    {
        "question": "Ðæt (<em>scip</em>) #### sceal genægled⁠ — The ship must be nailed",
        "correctAnswer": "scip",
        "explanation": "Here 'scip' is the subject and so takes no ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ðæs cyninges (<em>word</em>) #### is soþ⁠ — The king's word is truth",
        "correctAnswer": "word",
        "explanation": "Here 'word' is the subject and so takes no ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Godes (<em>bearn</em>) #### þrowode on þære rood⁠ — God's son suffered on the cross",
        "correctAnswer": "bearn",
        "explanation": "Here 'bearn' is the subject and so takes no ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ðæt (<em>wif</em>) #### wæs gehæled of ðam wite⁠ — The woman was healed of the disease",
        "correctAnswer": "wif",
        "explanation": "Here 'wif' is the subject and so takes no ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Hira (<em>god</em>) #### syndon drycræfta lareowas⁠ — Their gods are teachers of magical arts",
        "correctAnswer": "godu",
        "explanation": "Here 'god' is the subject and plural, so since 'god' has a short syllable it takes a 'u' ending",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "god",
                "explanation": "Here 'god' is the subject and plural, but since 'god' has a short syllable it should take a 'u' ending"
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "Ða (<em>scip</em>) #### Norðmanna cam on þissum dæg⁠ — The Northmen's ships came on this day",
        "correctAnswer": "scipu",
        "explanation": "Here 'scip' is the subject and plural, so since 'scip' has a short syllable it takes a 'u' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Gif þa (<em>word</em>) #### sind soþ⁠ — If the words are true",
        "correctAnswer": "word",
        "explanation": "Here 'word' is the subject and plural, so since 'word' has a long syllable it takes no ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Geata (<em>bearn</em>) #### ferde to him⁠ — The children of the Geats went to him ",
        "correctAnswer": "bearn",
        "explanation": "Here 'bearn' is the subject and plural, so since 'bearn' has a long syllable it takes no ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Seo geofu wæs broht for ðære synne ðæs ærestan (<em>wif</em>) ####⁠ — The grace was brought for the sin of the first woman",
        "correctAnswer": "wifes",
        "explanation": "Here 'wif' is in the genitive singular, so it takes the 'es' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "He wæs hiora (<em>god</em>) #### preost⁠ — He was the priest of their god",
        "correctAnswer": "godes",
        "explanation": "Here 'god' is in the genitive singular, so it takes the 'es' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Þæs (<em>scip</em>) #### mæst geburnen⁠ — The ship's mast burned",
        "correctAnswer": "scipes",
        "explanation": "Here 'scip' is in the genitive singular, so it takes the 'es' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Þæt þurh (<em>bearn</em>) #### gebyrd butan weres frigum, byrd eacen wearð⁠ — Through the bearing of a child without a man's embrace, that bride became great",
        "correctAnswer": "bearnes",
        "explanation": "Here 'bearn' is in the genitive singular, so it takes the 'es' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Seo is sæd ærest (<em>wif</em>) #### in Norþanhymbra mægþe ðæt heo munuchade onfenge⁠ — She is said to have been one of the first women in Northumbria to have taken nun-hood",
        "correctAnswer": "wifa",
        "explanation": "Here 'wif' is in the genitive plural, so it takes the 'a' ending",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "wif",
                "explanation": "Here 'wif' is in the genitive plural as she is 'one of the first', so it takes the 'a' ending"
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "On þis dæg, com þæs hæthenes (<em>god</em>) #### wigan⁠ — On that day, the warriors of the heathen gods came",
        "correctAnswer": "goda",
        "explanation": "Here 'god' is in the genitive plural, so it takes the 'a' ending",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "godes",
                "explanation": "Here 'god' is in the genitive plural, so it takes the 'a' ending, not the singular 'es' ending"
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "Ða het se cyning (<em>scip</em>) #### gegearcian⁠ — Then the king ordered the preparation of ships",
        "correctAnswer": "scipa",
        "explanation": "Here 'scip' is in the genitive plural, so it takes the 'a' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Hlosna to þæs Godes (<em>word</em>) ####⁠ — Listen to the word of God",
        "correctAnswer": "word",
        "explanation": "Here 'word' is in the singular accusative, and so takes no ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "He Noe gebletsade and his (<em>bearn</em>) ####⁠ — He blessed Noah and his child",
        "correctAnswer": "bearn",
        "explanation": "Here 'bearn' is in the singular accusative, and so takes no ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "He spræc to þæt (<em>wif</em>) ####⁠ — He spoke to the woman",
        "correctAnswer": "wif",
        "explanation": "Here 'wif' is in the singular accusative, and so takes no ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ða godu fram Egiptum landum beoþ fremede #### ⁠ — The gods from Egypt are strange gods",
        "correctAnswer": "godu",
        "explanation": "Here 'god' is the direct object and plural, so since 'god' has a short syllable it takes a 'u' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "He wolde geseean helle (<em>god</em>) ####⁠ — He would visit the gods of hell",
        "correctAnswer": "godu",
        "explanation": "Here 'god' is the direct object and plural, so since 'god' has a short syllable it takes a 'u' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ðæt wæron þa erestan (<em>scip</em>) #### Deniscra manna the Angelcynnes land geseah⁠ — Those were the first ships of Danish men the English people's land saw",
        "correctAnswer": "scipu",
        "explanation": "Here 'scip' is the direct object and plural, so since 'god' has a short syllable it takes a 'u' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Hie writon micel (<em>word</em>) #### lofa⁠ — They wrote many words of praise",
        "correctAnswer": "word",
        "explanation": "Here 'word' is the direct object and plural, so since 'word' has a long syllable it takes no ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se fæder wið-soc eall to his (<em>bearn</em>) ####⁠ — The father denied all to his child",
        "correctAnswer": "bearne",
        "explanation": "Here 'bearn' is the indirect object and singular, and so takes an 'e' ending",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "bearn",
                "explanation": "Here 'bearn' is the indirect object and singular, and so takes an 'e' ending. It is 'eall' which is the direct object"
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "And mon mot feohtan orwige gif he gemeteþ oðerne æt his æwum (<em>wif</em>) ####⁠ — And a man can fight without charge of homicide if he finds another with his lawful wife",
        "correctAnswer": "wife",
        "explanation": "Here 'wif' is the indirect object and singular, and so takes an 'e' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Seo cwen geaf þa boc to þæm ####⁠ — The queen gave the book to the woman",
        "correctAnswer": "wife",
        "explanation": "Here 'wif' is the indirect object and singular, and so takes an 'e' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "We willaþ mid þam sceattum us to þæm (<em>scip</em>) #### gangan⁠ — We wish to go to the ship with the treasure",
        "correctAnswer": "scipe",
        "explanation": "Here 'scip' is the indirect object and singular, and so takes an 'e' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "He ærist scoop eorþan for his (<em>bearn</em>) ####⁠ — He first shaped the earth for his children",
        "correctAnswer": "bearnum",
        "explanation": "Here 'bearn' is the indirect object and plural, and so takes a 'um' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Heo geaf micel giefa to þæm (<em>wif</em>) ####⁠ — She gave many gifts to the women",
        "correctAnswer": "wifum",
        "explanation": "Here 'wif' is the indirect object and plural, and so takes a 'um' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Hie bædon to hiora (<em>god</em>) ####⁠ — They prayed to their gods",
        "correctAnswer": "godum",
        "explanation": "Here 'god' is the indirect object and plural, and so takes a 'um' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se here ferde to þæm #### (<em>scip</em>)⁠ — The army went to the ships",
        "correctAnswer": "scipum",
        "explanation": "Here 'scip' is the indirect object and plural, and so takes a 'um' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Seo (<em>cwen</em>) #### ferþ to þæm beorgum⁠ — The queen goes to the mountains",
        "correctAnswer": "cwen",
        "explanation": "Here 'cwen' is the subject and so takes no ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Wæs (<em>giefu</em>) #### Hroþgares oft geæhted⁠ — The gift of Hrothgar was often prized",
        "correctAnswer": "giefu",
        "explanation": "Here 'giefu' is the subject and so takes no ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Seo (<em>ceaster</em>) #### ne mæg beon behyd⁠ — The city cannot be hidden",
        "correctAnswer": "ceaster",
        "explanation": "Here 'ceaster' is the subject and so takes no ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Sceolde monig blachleor (<em>ides</em>) #### bifiende gan⁠ — Many a pale-faced lady must trembling go",
        "correctAnswer": "ides",
        "explanation": "Here 'ides' is the subject and so takes no ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Þa (<em>cwen</em>) #### wæron hatene Marsepia and Lampida⁠ — The queens were called Marsepia and Lampida",
        "correctAnswer": "cwena",
        "explanation": "Here 'cwen' is the subject and plural, so it takes an 'a' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ðæt hie ælmihtiges (<em>giefu</em>) #### anforleten⁠ — That they might lose the almighty's gifts",
        "correctAnswer": "giefa",
        "explanation": "Here 'giefu' is the subject and plural, so it loses its 'u' takes an 'a' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ða (<em>ceaster</em>) ####, Gleawanceaster, Cirenceaster and Baþanceaster, beoþ on ceastrum weallum beworhte⁠ — The cities, Gloucester, Cirencester and Bath, are walled towns",
        "correctAnswer": "ceastra",
        "explanation": "Here 'ceastra' is the subject and plural, so it loses its second 'e' takes an 'a' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ða (<em>ides</em>) #### sloh ða wundenlocc þone feondsceaðan⁠ — The women slew the wavy-haired fiend",
        "correctAnswer": "idesa",
        "explanation": "Here 'ides' is the subject and plural, so it takes an 'a' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Heo ferde to þære (<em>cwen</em>) #### broce ond fram þære cwene broce⁠ — She went to the Queen's brook and from the Queen's brook",
        "correctAnswer": "cwene",
        "explanation": "Here 'cwen' is in the posessive singular, so it takes an 'e' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ðære (<em>ceaster</em>) #### ealdorman spræc mid þæm biscope⁠ — The city's elderman spoke with the bishop",
        "correctAnswer": "ceastre",
        "explanation": "Here 'ceaster' is in the posessive singular, so it loses its second 'e' and takes an 'e' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ðæra oðer wæs (<em>ides</em>) #### onlicnes⁠ — The other had a woman's likeness",
        "correctAnswer": "idese",
        "explanation": "Here 'ides' is in the posessive singular, so it takes an 'a' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "He wæs on ðara (<em>cwen</em>) #### gewealdum⁠ — He was under the power of the queens",
        "correctAnswer": "cwena",
        "explanation": "Here 'cwen' is in the posessive plural, so it takes an 'a' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ðara (<em>ceaster</em>) #### wisra menn ferde to þæm cyning⁠ — The cities wise men went to the king ",
        "correctAnswer": "ceastra",
        "explanation": "Here 'ceaster' is in the posessive plural, so it loses its second 'e' and takes an 'a' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ðara (<em>ides</em>) #### fæder wæs sæt æt wine⁠ — The ladies father was sat at his wine",
        "correctAnswer": "idesa",
        "explanation": "Here 'ides' is in the posessive plural, so it takes an 'a' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ic wæs feaxhar (<em>cwen</em>) ####⁠ — I was a hoary-haired woman",
        "correctAnswer": "cwene",
        "explanation": "Here 'cwen' is the direct object and singular, so it takes an 'e' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Heo gefylled wæs wisdomes (<em>giefu</em>) ####⁠ — She was filled with wisdom's gift ",
        "correctAnswer": "giefe",
        "explanation": "Here 'giefu' is the direct object and singular, so it loses its 'u' and takes an 'e' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ælla and Cissa ymbsæton þa (<em>ceaster</em>) ####⁠ — Aella and Cissa beseiged the city",
        "correctAnswer": "ceastre",
        "explanation": "Here 'ceaster' is the direct object and singular, so it loses its second 'e' and takes an 'e' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Weras and (<em>ides</em>) #### sceolan læran Godes lufan⁠ — Men and women shall learn God's love",
        "correctAnswer": "idesa",
        "explanation": "Here 'ides' is the subject and plural, so it takes an 'a' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ða þegnas læston þa (<em>cwen</em>) ####⁠ — The thanes followed the Queens",
        "correctAnswer": "cwena",
        "explanation": "Here 'cwen' is the direct object and plural, so it takes an 'a' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se Hælend ymbfor ealle þa burga ond þa (<em>ceaster</em>) ####⁠ — Jesus went around all the villages and the cities",
        "correctAnswer": "ceastra",
        "explanation": "Here 'ceaster' is the direct object and plural, so it loses its second 'e' and takes an 'a' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "To saulum on heofonum þu selest weorþlica (<em>giefu</em>) ####⁠ — To the souls in heaven you will give worthy gifts",
        "correctAnswer": "giefa",
        "explanation": "Here 'giefu' is the direct object and plural, so it loses its 'u' and takes an 'a' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ða comon ða weardas to þære (<em>ceaster</em>) ####⁠ — Then the keepers came into the city",
        "correctAnswer": "ceastre",
        "explanation": "Here 'ceaster' is an indirect object and singular, so it loses its second 'e' and takes an 'e' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ða þegnas ferde to þære (<em>ides</em>) ####⁠ — The thanes went to the lady",
        "correctAnswer": "idese",
        "explanation": "Here 'ides' is an indirect object and singular, so it takes an 'e' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Hie to ðære (<em>cwen</em>) #### agefon him⁠ — Then they gave him up to the queen",
        "correctAnswer": "cwene",
        "explanation": "Here 'cwen' is an indirect object and singular, so it takes an 'e' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "He ferde to þæm ceastre mid þæs cyninges (<em>giefu</em>) ####⁠ — He went to the city with the king's gift ",
        "correctAnswer": "giefe",
        "explanation": "Here 'giefu' is an indirect object and singular, so it loses its 'u' and takes an 'e' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Hlynn wearþ on þæm (<em>ceaster</em>) ####⁠ — A great cry arose in the cities",
        "correctAnswer": "ceastrum",
        "explanation": "Here 'ceaster' is an indirect object and plural, so it loses its second 'e' and takes a 'um' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "He geaf þa bec to þæm (<em>ides</em>) ####⁠ — He gave the books to the ladies",
        "correctAnswer": "idesum",
        "explanation": "Here 'ides' is an indirect object and plural, so it takes a 'um' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ða þegnas geaf begas ond feoh to þæm (<em>cwen</em>) ####⁠ — The thanes gave rings and wealth to the queens",
        "correctAnswer": "cwenum",
        "explanation": "Here 'cwen' is an indirect object and plural, so it takes a 'um' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ðin mod trymeþ mid godcundum (<em>giefu</em>) ####⁠ — Strengthen your mind with divine gifts",
        "correctAnswer": "giefum",
        "explanation": "Here 'giefu' is an indirect object and plural, so it takes a 'um' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ðæs <em>(biscop)</em> #### swearta stan  — The bishop’s black stone",
        "correctAnswer": "biscopes",
        "explanation": "Here 'biscop' is in the singular genitive so it takes the 'es' ending",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "biscopa",
                "explanation": "While 'biscop' is in the genitive, it is the singular 'biscopes'. Biscopa' is the genitive plural"
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "Se <em>(þegen)</em> #### ond þa biscops fram Readingum — The thane and the bishops from Reading",
        "correctAnswer": "þegen",
        "explanation": "Here 'þegen' is the subject so it takes the nominative singular case",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ðæs cyninges <em>(þegen)</em> #### ferde to þæm tune — The king’s thanes went to the town",
        "correctAnswer": "þegnas|þegenas",
        "explanation": "Here 'þegen' is the subject and in the plural, so it takes the 'as' ending of the plural nominative",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "þegen",
                "explanation": "While not apparant in the Old English, þegen is clearly plural in the modern English trans, and so takes the 'as' ending of the nominative plural"
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "Ða <em>(cyning)</em> #### ond þa biscopas on Æscesdune — The kings and the bishops in Ashdown",
        "correctAnswer": "cyningas",
        "explanation": "Here 'cyning' is the subject and plural so it takes the 'as' ending of the nominative plural",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "cyning",
                "explanation": "'Cyning' is the singular form of the word while the above word is plural. This means the correct answer is 'cyningas'. If you're not sure whether a word is plural or singular, check the demonstrative pronoun."
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "Eall þara <em>(biscop)</em> #### preostas ferde to þæm halige stede mid him — All the bishops’ priests went to the holy place with them",
        "correctAnswer": "biscopa",
        "explanation": "Here 'biscop' is in the possessive plural, since there are multiple priests belong to multiple bishops, so it takes the 'a' ending of the genitive plural",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "biscopas",
                "explanation": "Biscopas is the nominative or accusative plural. The genitive plural ends in 'a', so the correct answer is 'biscopa'."
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "In Þæs (<i>cyning</i>) #### tune — In the town of the king",
        "correctAnswer": "cyninges",
        "explanation": "Here 'cyning' is in the possessive singular so it takes the 'es' ending of the genitive singular",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ða þegnas þara <em>(cyning)</em> #### Ælfred and Æþelred — The thane's of the Kings' Alfred and Ethelred",
        "correctAnswer": "cyninga",
        "explanation": "Here 'cyning' is in the possessive plural so it takes the 'a' ending of the genitive plural",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se (<i>biscop</i>) #### fram þæm tune — The bishop from the town",
        "correctAnswer": "biscop",
        "explanation": "Here 'biscop' is the subject and in the singular so it takes no ending, as per the nominative singular",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ða Þegnas ond se (<i>cyning</i>) #### — The thanes and the king",
        "correctAnswer": "cyning",
        "explanation": "Here 'cyning' is subject and in the singular so it takes no ending, as per the nominative singular",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Fram þæs (<i>þegen</i>) #### tune — From the thane’s town",
        "correctAnswer": "þegnes|þegenes",
        "explanation": "Here 'þegen' is in the possessive singular so it takes the 'es' ending of the genitive singular",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se cyning ond þa (<i>biscop</i>) #### — The king and the bishops",
        "correctAnswer": "biscopas",
        "explanation": "Here 'biscop' is part of the subject and plural so it takes the 'as' ending of the nominative plural",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ðæs (<i>þegen</i>) #### menn — The thane’s men",
        "correctAnswer": "þegnes|þegenes",
        "explanation": "Here 'þegen' is in the possessive singular so it takes the 'es' ending of the genitive singular",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Menn fram Þara (<i>þegen</i>) #### tunum — Men from the towns of the thanes",
        "correctAnswer": "þegna|þegena",
        "explanation": "Here 'þegen' is in the possessive plural as the men are from towns belonging to the thanes, so it takes the 'a' ending of the genitive plural",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ða <em>(stan)</em> #### fram þæs þegnes tune — The stone from the thane’s town",
        "correctAnswer": "stanas",
        "explanation": "Here 'stan' is subject and is plural so it takes the 'as' ending of the nominative plural",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se (<i>stan</i>) #### ond se þegen — The stone and the thane",
        "correctAnswer": "stan",
        "explanation": "Here 'stan' is subject and in the singular so it takes no ending, as per the nominative singular",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ðara <em>(wicing)</em> #### cyning wolde þæt þa Deniscan ricsoden ofer Englalande⁠ — The king of the viking's would that the Danes ruled over England",
        "correctAnswer": "wicinga",
        "explanation": "Here 'wicing' is in the possessive plural as the subject is the king of many vikings, so 'wicing' takes the 'a' ending of the genitive plural",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ða bearn þæs <em>(cyning)</em> #### beoþ wis and eaþmod⁠ — The children of the king are wise and humble",
        "correctAnswer": "cyninges",
        "explanation": "Here 'cyning' is in the possessive singular so it takes the 'es' ending of the genitive singular",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ða <em>(biscop)</em> #### geaf þone stan to þæm þegne — The bishops gave the stone to the thane",
        "correctAnswer": "biscopas",
        "explanation": "Here 'biscop' is the subject and it is plural so it takes the 'as' ending of the nominative plural",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Giet wæs se <em>(cyning)</em> #### Ælfred geong⁠ — Still, the king Alfred was young",
        "correctAnswer": "cyning",
        "explanation": "Here 'cyning' is the subject and in the singular so it takes no ending, as per the nominative singular",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se biscop grete þone (<i>cyning</i>) #### — The bishop greets the king",
        "correctAnswer": "cyning",
        "explanation": "Here 'cyning' is directly receiving the action of the verb 'grete', so is in the singular accusative and thus takes no new ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "þa biscopas geaf þone (<i>stan</i>) #### to þæm þegne — The bishops gave the stone to the thane",
        "correctAnswer": "stan",
        "explanation": "Here 'stan' is directly receiving the action of the verb 'geaf', so is in the singular accusative and thus takes no new ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se þegen sloh þone (<i>biscop</i>) #### in þæm tune — The thane slew the bishop in the town",
        "correctAnswer": "biscop",
        "explanation": "Here 'biscop' is directly receiving the action of the verb 'sloh', so is in the singular accusative and thus takes no new ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se cyning ond seo cwen grete þa (<i>biscop</i>) #### — The king and the queen greet the bishops",
        "correctAnswer": "biscopas",
        "explanation": "Here 'biscop' is directly receiving the action of the verb 'grete' and is also plural, so it is in the plural accusative and thus takes the 'as' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se cyning sloh þa (<i>þegen</i>) #### — The king slew the thanes",
        "correctAnswer": "þegnas|þegenas",
        "explanation": "Here 'þegen' is directly receiving the action of the verb 'sloh' and is also plural, so it is in the plural accusative and thus takes the 'as' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se þegen geaf þa (<i>gar</i>) #### to þæm cyninge — The thane gave the spears to the king",
        "correctAnswer": "garas",
        "explanation": "Here 'gar' is directly receiving the action of the verb 'geaf' and is also plural, so it is in the plural accusative and thus takes the 'as' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "To þæm biscop geaf se cyning þa (<i>beag</i>) #### — The king gave rings to the bishop",
        "correctAnswer": "beagas",
        "explanation": "Here 'beag' is directly receiving the action of the verb 'geaf' and is also plural, so it is in the plural accusative and thus takes the 'as' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "To þæm (<i>cyning</i>) #### se biscop geaf beag — To the king, the bishop gave a ring",
        "correctAnswer": "cyninge",
        "explanation": "Here 'cyning' is not directly receiving the action of the verb 'geaf', so it is in the singular dative and thus takes the 'e' ending.",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se þegen ferþ to þæm (<i>biscop</i>) #### mid wordum fram þæm cyning — The thane goes to the bishop with words from the king",
        "correctAnswer": "biscope",
        "explanation": "Here 'biscop' is not directly receiving the action of the verb 'ferþ', so it is in the singular dative and thus takes the 'e' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se biscop ferde fram þæm (<i>þegen</i>) #### to þæm cyning — The bishop went from the thane to the king",
        "correctAnswer": "þegne|þegene",
        "explanation": "Here 'þegen' is not directly receiving the action of the verb 'ferde', so it is in the singular dative and thus takes the 'e' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "On þis dæg, Æðelred cyning ferde to þæm (<i>tun</i>) #### mid broðor— On this day, King Ethelred went to the town his brother",
        "correctAnswer": "tune",
        "explanation": "Here 'tun' is not directly receiving the action of the verb 'ferde', so it is in the singular dative and thus takes the 'e' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se cyning ferþ to þæm (<i>beorg</i>) #### — The king goes to the mountains",
        "correctAnswer": "beorgum",
        "explanation": "Here 'beorg' is not directly receiving the action of the verb 'ferþ', so it is in the singular dative and thus takes the 'e' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Wærferhþ biscop ferde to þæm (<i>biscop</i>) #### in Lundene ond Wiltunscire — Bishop Warfehth went to the bishops of London and Wiltshire",
        "correctAnswer": "biscopum",
        "explanation": "Here 'biscop' is not directly receiving the action of the verb 'ferde', so it is in the singular dative and thus takes the 'e' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se geaf þa garas to þæm (<i>þegen</i>) #### — He gave the spears to the thanes",
        "correctAnswer": "þegnum|þegenum",
        "explanation": "Here 'þegen' is not directly receiving the action of the verb 'geaf', so it is in the singular dative and thus takes the 'e' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "þa biscopas came fram þæm (<i>tun</i>) #### hetum Londenum ond Readingum — The bishops came from the towns called London and Reading",
        "correctAnswer": "tunum",
        "explanation": "Here 'tun' is not directly receiving the action of the verb 'came', so it is in the singular dative and thus takes the 'e' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ðæt (<em>wite</em>) #### wæs strang⁠ — The punishment was strong",
        "correctAnswer": "wite",
        "explanation":"Here 'wite' is the subject and so takes no ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ða halgan (<em>sawol</em>) #### sint undeaþlice and ece⁠ — The holy souls are undying and eternal",
        "correctAnswer": "sawla",
        "explanation":"Here 'sawol' is the subject and plural, so it loses its unstressed 'o' takes an 'a' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Nilt ðu habban yfelan (<em>scoh</em>) ####⁠ — You do not want to have an evil shoe",
        "correctAnswer": "scoh",
        "explanation":"Here 'scoh' is masculine, the direct object and single, so it takes no ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Hie heora (<em>heafod</em>) #### slogan on ða wagas⁠ — They struck their heads against the walls",
        "correctAnswer": "heafdu",
        "explanation":"Here 'heafod' is neuter, the direct object and plural so it loses its unstressed 'o' and gains a u",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ðæs (<em>fugol</em>) #### flyht wæs dyrne and degol⁠ — The bird's flight was hidden and secret",
        "correctAnswer": "fugles",
        "explanation":"'Fugol' is masculine and here it is possessive and single so it loses its unstressed 'o' and gains an 'es' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ðara (<em>wealh</em>) #### cyning slog monige menn⁠ — The King of the foreigners slew many men",
        "correctAnswer": "weala",
        "explanation":"'Wealh' is masculine and here it is the posessive plural, so it loses its 'h' and gains an 'a' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Sume wæron mid iserne (<em>clawu</em>) #### totorene⁠ — Some were torn with an icy claw",
        "correctAnswer": "clawe",
        "explanation":"'Clawu' is feminine and here it is a singular, indirect object so it loses its final vowel, 'u', and gains an 'e' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "God ricsaþ on feower (<em>ende</em>) #### ðyses middangeardes⁠ — God rules in the four corners of the earth",
        "correctAnswer": "endum",
        "explanation":"Here 'ende' is an indirect object and plural, so it loses its final vowel, 'e', and gains a 'um' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Godes (<em>engel</em>) #### stod on emn him⁠ — God's angel stood before him",
        "correctAnswer": "engel",
        "explanation":"Here 'engel' is the subject and so takes no ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "He bletsode ða adrife (<em>fæt</em>) #### ond ða beagas⁠ — He blessed the engraved cups and the rings",
        "correctAnswer": "fatu",
        "explanation":"'Fæt' is neuter and here it is the direct object and plural, so its 'æ' changes to 'a' and it gains the 'u' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "He wæs on ðæs (<em>hwæl</em>) #### innoþe⁠ — He was in the whale's innards",
        "correctAnswer": "hwæles",
        "explanation":"Here 'hwæl' is in the possessive singular and so gains the 'es' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Her sindon nigon (<em>engel</em>) #### werod⁠ — Here are nine hosts of angels",
        "correctAnswer": "engla",
        "explanation":"Here 'engel' is in the posessive plural and so loses its unstressed 'e' and gains an 'a' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Hie coman on ðrim ceolum hider to Brytene on ðam (<em>stede</em>) #### Heopwines fleot⁠ — He came on three ships to Britain to the place called Heopwines fleet",
        "correctAnswer": "stede",
        "explanation":"Here 'stede' is an indirect object and singular, so it takes an 'e' ending. Since it already ends in 'e', and since end-vowels are dropped before a suffix, this makes it look like the word does not change",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "He wealdeþ sidum (<em>rice</em>) ####⁠ — He rules broad kingdoms",
        "correctAnswer": "ricum",
        "explanation":"Here 'rice' is in the posessive plural and so loses its end-vowel and gains the 'um' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Seo (<em>sceadu</em>) #### byþ to underne seofon and twentigoþan healfes fotes⁠ — The shadow is twenty-seven and a half feet at 9am",
        "correctAnswer": "sceadu",
        "explanation":"Here 'sceadu' is the subject and singular and so takes no ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ðu eart eallra þinga fruma and (<em>ende</em>) ####⁠ — You are the beginning and end of all things",
        "correctAnswer": "ende",
        "explanation":"Here 'ende' is the direct object and singular and so takes no ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "We habbaþ eowre (<em>scoh</em>) #### on eowrum fotum⁠ — We have our shoes on our feet",
        "correctAnswer": "scos",
        "explanation":"'Scoh' is masculine and here it is the direct object and plural so it should take an 'as' ending. Since it ends in 'h', it loses the 'h' and the unstressed vowel of the suffix when declined",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Seo ydelnes is ðære (<em>sawol</em>) #### feond⁠ — Idleness is the soul's enemy",
        "correctAnswer": "sawle",
        "explanation":"Here 'sawol' is in the posessive signular, so it loses its unstressed 'o' and gains the 'e' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "671 Her wæs ðæt micle (<em>fugol</em>) #### wæl⁠ — 671AD: here was the great slaughter of birds",
        "correctAnswer": "fugla",
        "explanation":"Here 'fugol' is in the possessive plural, so it loses its unstressed 'o' and gains the 'a' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "We sceolon fyligan urum (<em>heafod</em>) ####⁠ — We should follow our heads",
        "correctAnswer": "heafde",
        "explanation":"Here 'heafod' is an indirect object and singular, so it loses its unstressed 'o' and gains the 'e' ending",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "heafod",
                "explanation":"Here 'heafod' is an indirect object, not direct object, as the heads are not being directly acted upon. This means it takes the dative singular 'e' ending"
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "Heo wæs to manegum (<em>wite</em>) #### geworht⁠ — She was put to many tortures",
        "correctAnswer": "witum",
        "explanation":"Here 'wite' is an indirect object and plural, so it loses its end-vowel and takes the 'um' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Hira (<em>clawu</em>) #### todælede beoþ⁠ — Their hooves are divided",
        "correctAnswer": "clawa",
        "explanation":"Here 'clawu' is the subject and plural so it loses its end-vowel and gains the 'a' ending",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer": "clawas",
                "explanation":"'Clawu', like most words ending in 'u', is feminine, not masculine, so it takes the nominative plural 'a' ending"
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "He gewanode his (<em>feoh</em>) #### and geihte his rihtwisnysse⁠ — He dimished his wealth and increased his righteousness",
        "correctAnswer": "feoh",
        "explanation":"'Feoh' is neuter and here it is the direct object and singular, so takes no ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Wilt ðu fon (<em>hwæl</em>) ####?⁠ — Will you hunt whales?",
        "correctAnswer": "hwalas",
        "explanation":"Here 'hwæl' is the direct object and plural so its 'æ' changes to 'a' and it gains the 'as' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ic þe þa fæhðe leanige (<em>feoh</em>) #### ond ealdgestreonum, swa ic ær dyde⁠ — For the feud, I would reward you with wealth and old treasures, as I did before",
        "correctAnswer": "feo",
        "explanation":"Here 'feoh' is the indect object and singular so it loses its 'h'. It should take an 'e' ending but since it is an unstressed vowel, it takes no ending",
        "commonMistakes": [
            {
                "incorrectAnswer":"feoe",
                "explanation":"Here 'feoh' is the indect object and singular so it should take an 'e' ending, but since you drop the unstressed vowel along with the 'h', it takes no ending"
            }
        ]
    },
    {
        "question": "Ða hie sæton þara ond innan Ionan tu winter on þam twam (<em>stede</em>) ####⁠ — Then settled there and on the Yonne, two winters in those two places",
        "correctAnswer": "stedum",
        "explanation":"Here 'stede' is an indirect object and plural and so it drops its end-vowel and takes the 'um' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Se (<em>stede</em>) #### is halig ðe ðu on stenst⁠ — The place where you stand is holy ",
        "correctAnswer": "stede",
        "explanation":"Here 'stede' is the subject and singular, so it takes no ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "(<em>engel</em>) #### God worhte, ða sind gastas, and nabbaþ nænne lichaman ⁠ — God created angels, which are spirits and have no body",
        "correctAnswer": "englas",
        "explanation":"'Engel' is masculine and here it is the direct object, so it loses its unstressed 'e' and gains an 'as' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Eall Italia (<em>rice</em>) #### þæt betwux þam muntum ond Sicilia þam ealonde in anwald gerehton⁠ — All the kingdom of Italy that is between the mountains and the island of Sicily were subjugated",
        "correctAnswer": "rice",
        "explanation":"Here 'rice' is an indirect object and singular. Since it loses its end-vowel and gains an 'e', it looks like it does not gain an ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    },
    {
        "question": "Ic nu gange on midde þa (<em>sceadu</em>) #### deaðes, ne ondræde ic me nan yfel, forþam þu byst mid me⁠ — Though I walk through the valley of the shadow of death, I will fear no evil: for thou art with me",
        "correctAnswer": "sceade",
        "explanation":"Here 'sceadu' is an indirect object and singular, so it loses its end-vowel and gains the 'e' ending",
        "commonMistakes": []
    }
]